<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Transcriptomics | IRunFasterThanMyCode</title>
    <link>/tags/transcriptomics/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/transcriptomics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Transcriptomics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2017 Sam Robson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/irunfasterthanmycode.jpg</url>
      <title>Transcriptomics</title>
      <link>/tags/transcriptomics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Center for Enzyme Innovation</title>
      <link>/project/2019-06-18-center-for-enzyme-innovation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2019-06-18-center-for-enzyme-innovation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Enzyme Innovation is a new initiative set up at the University of Portsmouth, with a goal to find solutions to some of the most pressing global environmental problems. In particular, we aim to examine environmental samples to find how the natural world has solved the problem of plastic pollution, by identifying microorganisms who have evolved to be able to break down plastics in the environment. By identifying these microorgansisms, and further understanding the enzymatic methods that they use towards this goal, we aim to harness the amazing work that nature has done, and find ways to enhance this and scale it up on an industrial scale to allow their use in circular recycling of plastics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.port.ac.uk/enquire/news/portsmouth-scientists-awarded-major-plastics-funding&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;recently awarded £5.8 million&lt;/a&gt; in funding from the Research England Expanding Excellence Fund. Together with significant investment from the University of Portsmouth, we aim to use this funding to speed up our progress towards finding a solution to one of the world’s greatest environmental challenges – plastic waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be working in the Discovery phase of the pipeline, aiming to use next generation &lt;a href=&#34;https://nanoporetech.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nanopore&lt;/a&gt; sequencing to explore microorganisms present on samples taken from environmental sites of interest (e.g. plastic receycling centres) to try and profile what is present and how they have developed to survive on plastic substrates. We aim to use this bioprospecting approach to explore metagenomics and metatranscriptomics of samples to identify mechanisms of action for plastic degaradation, and in particular to compare with previously explored species to identify what makes these species unique. This information, and information on the make-up of enzymes involved in the processes, will feed through the pipeline to be further engineered to create enzymes that can be scaled up on an industrial scale. These data will be combined with data from public repositories to feed into novel machine learning algorithms to help to train algorithms for the identification of further potential candidates for feeding through the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in microbial communities of Cliona celeta during observed changes in sponge health</title>
      <link>/project/2017-09-29-microbial-community-of-cliona-celeta-during-observed-changes-in-sponge-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2017-09-29-microbial-community-of-cliona-celeta-during-observed-changes-in-sponge-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cliona celeta is a yellow boring sponge found around the waters of the UK. The diversity of sponges in the Skomer Marine Nature Reserve has been surveyed since the 1990s. In 2013 divers observed apparent disease in C. celeta individuals across Skomer Island and the Marloes Peninsula. The previously healthy yellow sponge became colonised by fouling organisms followed by tissue decay and patches of black necrotic sponge. This issue appears to be seasonal, largely seen between the months of March and October, and is the first recorded incidence of sponge disease in temperate coastal waters. In addition, several sponges were seen to be fouled by algal and invertebrate species, without progression to the black state, which is indicative of reduced anti-fouling mechanisms in the sponge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/dr-joanne-preston.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr Joanne Preston&lt;/a&gt;, we are working to identify the change in microbial communities following the shift between healthy and fouled or necrotic tissue in sponges based on microbiological culturing and 16S rDNA sequencing of the sponge host and the microbial communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Anti-Fouling Coatings on Marine Biofilms</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17-anti-fouling-marine-biofilms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17-anti-fouling-marine-biofilms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Marine biofilms, or &amp;ldquo;biofouling&amp;rdquo;, are communities of micro-organisms bound together on a surface by an extracellular matrix composed of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS). Biofilms consist predominantly of phytoplankton (particularly diatoms which are photosynthesising algae) and bacteria, which bind to surfaces in the marine environment to form complex 3 dimensional surface structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of these biofilms can affect all types of surfaces in the marine environment, and substrates include such man-made structures as the hulls of ships, nets used by fishing trawlers, pipelines used to transport oil and gas, and boat propellors. Biofilm formation on ships can have a costly impact due to increased drag - for example the increased cost of fuel has been estimated at around $56 million per year for DDG-51 naval ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason, testing novel antifouling substrates that are environmentally benign is of great importance to many marine-based industries. Working together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/maria-salta.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Maria Salta&lt;/a&gt; we have been analysing the changes in bacterial communities on different man-made surfaces using next-generation sequencing. This project combines microbiological analysis with both 16S rDNA amplicon sequencing (for populationa analysis) and whole transcriptome sequencing using RNA seq (for gene expression analysis).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Radiation Exposure in the Environment</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17-effect-of-radiation-exposure-on-fish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17-effect-of-radiation-exposure-on-fish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exposure to radiation can have deleterious effects on gene expression regulation, particularly due to increased DNA damage and deregulation of DNA damage checkpoint pathways. Working together with Dr. Adelaide Lerebours, we are performing differential expression analyses to understand the effects of radiation on 3-spined stickleback under laboratory conditions, and in particular attempting to characterise the differences between normal and abnormal offspring of exposed parents to understand how mutations are passed down through the lineage. In addition, we are looking at the effects of radiation exposure in the field, by looking at the effects of radiation exposure on lakes around the Chernobyl nuclear power station which suffered a catastrophic meltdown in 1986. The effects of this are still being felt today, and this project will allow us to understand the negative impact that this disaster has had on aquatic life in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gene Expression Profiling of Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17-expression-profiling-of-dmd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17-expression-profiling-of-dmd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD) is an X-linked recessive form of muscular dystrophy typically presenting in boys at around the age of four. DMD is caused by mutations in the DMD gene, which is the largest gene in the genome with 79 exons encoding a range of dystrophin proteins. These proteins are expressed in skeletal and cardiac muscles and also in brain and other non-muscle tissues, where they have specific roles. Their absence due to DMD mutations causes specific abnormalities such as progressive muscle weakness and wasting and cognitive deficits. Muscle weakness begins in the upper legs and pelvis but quickly spreads until boys are unable to walk and eventually cannot breathe unaided.  As yet, no cure exists for DMD, despite it being the most common form of muscular dystrophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-pharmacy-and-biomedical-sciences/staff/prof-darek-gorecki.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Professor Darek Gorecki&lt;/a&gt;, we are using RNA seq analysis to identify the changes in expression associated with a point mutation in the Dmd gene in a dystrophic mouse model. By identifying the pathways most impacted by the dystrophic phenotype, we hope to identify novel areas for future therapeutic intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Xenopus Development Project</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17-role-of-variant-histones-on-xenopus-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17-role-of-variant-histones-on-xenopus-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/prof-matt-guille.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Professor Matt Guille&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/dr-fiona-myers.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Fiona Myers&lt;/a&gt;, we are examining development in the model species &lt;em&gt;Xenopus laevis&lt;/em&gt;. We are using a wide range of techniques, including ChIP-seq to study epigenetic changes and to observe transcription factor binding throughout development, RNA-seq to study changes in gene expression, structural analysis of DNA tertiary structures, and Nanopore sequencing using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nanoporetech.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Oxford Nanopore MinION&lt;/a&gt; system to look at whole genome changes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
