<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Microbiology | IRunFasterThanMyCode</title>
    <link>/tags/microbiology/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/microbiology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Microbiology</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2017 Sam Robson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/irunfasterthanmycode.jpg</url>
      <title>Microbiology</title>
      <link>/tags/microbiology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biofilm Composition in Prosthetic Joint Infection</title>
      <link>/project/2020-02-23-biofilm-composition-in-prosthetic-joint-infection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2020-02-23-biofilm-composition-in-prosthetic-joint-infection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prosthetic joint infection (PJI) represents one of the most common reasons for failure among hip and knee arthroplasty, with an incidence of around 1-2%. Infection can occur early (within days of surgery) or late (over a year after surgery), and no specific early markers for infection onset exist. Given the significant costs to the NHS for corrective revision surgery, the added suffering and risks to patients from surgery, and the risk of enhancing antimicrobial resistance through the use of broad-spectrum antibiotics, a more specific predictive test for early onset of infection is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 80% of human infection is estimated to be a result of biofilm formation. Biofilms are an accumulation of microorganisms on a surface, resulting in a functional community which provides antibiotic resistance and a beneficial environment for the growth of pathogenic species that would otherwise be removed by the body’s defences. Biofilms can rupture, allowing pathogens to spread infection. To date, biofilm development and diversity on periprosthetic implants is poorly understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are exploring biofilm formation on hip joint prostheses using techniques including next generation sequencing (NGS) and 3D phase-contrast X-ray microscopy, and aim to compare bacterial diversity and biofilm structure between infected and non-infected samples. Our goal is to identify novel biomarkers using an innovative inter-disciplinary approach, which can be tested in a clinical setting in a sustainable and highly impactful research program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Anti-Fouling Coatings on Marine Biofilms</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17-anti-fouling-marine-biofilms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17-anti-fouling-marine-biofilms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Marine biofilms, or &amp;ldquo;biofouling&amp;rdquo;, are communities of micro-organisms bound together on a surface by an extracellular matrix composed of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS). Biofilms consist predominantly of phytoplankton (particularly diatoms which are photosynthesising algae) and bacteria, which bind to surfaces in the marine environment to form complex 3 dimensional surface structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of these biofilms can affect all types of surfaces in the marine environment, and substrates include such man-made structures as the hulls of ships, nets used by fishing trawlers, pipelines used to transport oil and gas, and boat propellors. Biofilm formation on ships can have a costly impact due to increased drag - for example the increased cost of fuel has been estimated at around $56 million per year for DDG-51 naval ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason, testing novel antifouling substrates that are environmentally benign is of great importance to many marine-based industries. Working together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/maria-salta.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Maria Salta&lt;/a&gt; we have been analysing the changes in bacterial communities on different man-made surfaces using next-generation sequencing. This project combines microbiological analysis with both 16S rDNA amplicon sequencing (for populationa analysis) and whole transcriptome sequencing using RNA seq (for gene expression analysis).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
