<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Microbiology | IRunFasterThanMyCode</title>
    <link>/tags/microbiology/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/microbiology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Microbiology</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2017 Sam Robson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/irunfasterthanmycode.jpg</url>
      <title>Microbiology</title>
      <link>/tags/microbiology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in microbial communities of Cliona celeta during observed changes in sponge health</title>
      <link>/project/2017-09-29_microbial_community_of_cliona_celeta_during_observed_changes_in_sponge_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2017-09-29_microbial_community_of_cliona_celeta_during_observed_changes_in_sponge_health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cliona celeta is a yellow boring sponge found around the waters of the UK. The diversity of sponges in the Skomer Marine Nature Reserve has been surveyed since the 1990s. In 2013 divers observed apparent disease in C. celeta individuals across Skomer Island and the Marloes Peninsula. The previously healthy yellow sponge became colonised by fouling organisms followed by tissue decay and patches of black necrotic sponge. This issue appears to be seasonal, largely seen between the months of March and October, and is the first recorded incidence of sponge disease in temperate coastal waters. In addition, several sponges were seen to be fouled by algal and invertebrate species, without progression to the black state, which is indicative of reduced anti-fouling mechanisms in the sponge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/dr-joanne-preston.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr Joanne Preston&lt;/a&gt;, we are working to identify the change in microbial communities following the shift between healthy and fouled or necrotic tissue in sponges based on microbiological culturing and 16S rDNA sequencing of the sponge host and the microbial communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Anti-Fouling Coatings on Marine Biofilms</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17_anti-fouling-marine-biofilms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17_anti-fouling-marine-biofilms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Marine biofilms, or &amp;ldquo;biofouling&amp;rdquo;, are communities of micro-organisms bound together on a surface by an extracellular matrix composed of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS). Biofilms consist predominantly of phytoplankton (particularly diatoms which are photosynthesising algae) and bacteria, which bind to surfaces in the marine environment to form complex 3 dimensional surface structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of these biofilms can affect all types of surfaces in the marine environment, and substrates include such man-made structures as the hulls of ships, nets used by fishing trawlers, pipelines used to transport oil and gas, and boat propellors. Biofilm formation on ships can have a costly impact due to increased drag - for example the increased cost of fuel has been estimated at around $56 million per year for DDG-51 naval ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason, testing novel antifouling substrates that are environmentally benign is of great importance to many marine-based industries. Working together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/maria-salta.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Maria Salta&lt;/a&gt; we have been analysing the changes in bacterial communities on different man-made surfaces using next-generation sequencing. This project combines microbiological analysis with both 16S rDNA amplicon sequencing (for populationa analysis) and whole transcriptome sequencing using RNA seq (for gene expression analysis).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
